what happened so now we've got to the
point where the story says while human
beings became self-conscious and here's
here's the problem with that the problem
is is that we're terribly self-conscious
about our inadequacies and our
vulnerabilities and that that sets up
enmity between men and women and it
dooms women to pain in childbirth and
child-rearing and it dooms men to work
it's a big problem okay so now the next
story that comes up in the sequence is
the story of Cain and Abel now you know
we talked about the dragon of chaos and
then the terrible mother and the
creative mother and on the tyrannical
father and the secure father and then
the adversary and the hero Cain and Abel
are the first manifestation of the
adversary and the hero and what happens
is they emerge as soon as the genesis in
the original Genesis story ends so what
the story basically proposes is that
once people became self conscious two
modes of being emerged as a consequence
of that and one mode is represented by
Cain and the other mode is represented
by Abel and that's echoed in the story
of the hostile brothers in stories of
hostile brothers everywhere but it's
also paralleled in Christianity by the
idea of the relationship between Christ
and Satan so it's like Cain and Abel are
precursors to the idea of Christ and and
and and Satan now what happens is that
so
Cain is the older brother and that makes
him sort of the embodiment of tradition
he would also be the favored one in
terms of the traditions of the ancient
Israelites because he would be the one
that inherits everyone so everything so
he's actually the one that's he's like
the embodiment of tradition and there's
some add some advantages to that because
he's privileged because of it but
there's some disadvantages because to
the degree that culture itself has
become sterile and inappropriate and he
manifests that that means that he
manifests error by merely being what he
was now what happens with an enable is
the young is the young brother so
Abel was a keeper of sheep but Cain was
a tiller of the ground
okay so there's there's a there's a
dichotomy of professions here and people
have read that in all sorts of different
ways but one of the ways that you can
think about it is that there are valid
different modes of being in the world
you know so you can be in this situation
you can be a tiller of the ground or a
keeper of animals but in the world in
general you can adopt any number of
rules that suffice you can be a plumber
or you can be a lawyer and there are
there's there's ways of acting within
those rules that transcend the rules
themselves and so that's part of what's
being exemplified in Cain and Abel so
they can they can function in the world
despite their different their different
roles in process of time it came to pass
that Cain brought of the fruit of the
ground an offering unto the Lord and
Abel he also brought of the firstlings
of his flock and of the fat thereof now
that's very archaic the idea of
sacrifice okay so basically what happens
is that you're trying to get God on your
side and so God seems to want something
from you because he keeps demanding this
and that so you might say well reality
wants something from you it wants you to
behave in a certain way so that you
don't suffer any more than you have to
and so that things go well for you now
human beings at this point in time are
trying to work out exactly what that
means and they've already got to the
point where they're conceptually
sophisticated enough to understand that
that means that sacrifices are necessary
now you remember that it's only prior to
this that human beings discover time
itself right that's when they discovered
that they're they become self conscious
and discover their extension across time
and so one of the consequences of
realizing that your extended across time
is that you also will come to the
realization that you may have to let go
of certain valuable things right now in
order to make things work better in the
future and you can't imagine that people
just woke up and figure that out
I cook people god only knows how long to
sort that out it's tens of thousands of
years to come up with that realization
first of all they would have acted it
out like bees do you know they collect
honey and they make it through the
winter but they don't know what the hell
they're doing or maybe they do maybe
they're little supercomputers like these
bloody atoms but you know what I mean
you can out
this sort of thing out without realizing
what you're up to and the motif of
sacrifice seemed to be exactly that
people stumbled on to the dramatic idea
that if you gave up something of value
there would be some reasonable
possibility that God would smile on you
in the future okay so so that's why
there's the sacrifices now you might say
well why did they burn them and the
reason for that is well as far as I can
tell people are trying to understand
what the ultimate fabric of existence is
and I think that you can feel that
sometimes in one of the places that
people feel that regularly is when
they're out at night and they look up at
the sky and they see this immense
blanket of eternity that's laid out
before them and that induces a feeling
of awe and I think that that archaic
people took the notion of that awe that
was a consequence of this apprehension
and associated that with some something
like communion with the divine which is
actually quite reasonable because when
you are looking out into space you are
looking into the farthest reaches of
being you can see back millions hundreds
of millions of years back into time and
you see you gaze out into the infinite
expanses of being so it's not
unreasonable to assume that in some
sense at that moment you have some
connection with what's infinite whatever
that happens to be and I think that you
feel that rather than thinking so
anyways the idea basically emerged that
the divine was up in the sky and that
because the divine was up in the sky you
could maybe communicate it with it by
sending messages up there and one of the
ways you could do that was with smoke
and so if you're burning these things
that you're offering you get to push the
smoke up to God and he can do a
molecular analysis and see if what
you're offering is of any reasonable
quality and if it seems to me then poof
you know God's gonna be thrilled about
that
or maybe he's not now what happens is
that Cain's offerings are rejected and
Abel's offerings are accepted and so
what that means is that Cain gets the
short end of the stick and Abel gets
everything good happening to him so what
you see happening is that there's the
notion of two paths of being one that's
favored and one that isn't favored now
the story is very ambivalent about why
Cain is not favored and Abel is and you
you
can you can read it multiple ways you
can just say well guards basically being
a son of a and he's not gonna give
Katie anything just because he's not in
a very good mood that day or you can say
well Abel's doing something right and
Cain isn't and I think that interpreting
the story in either of those ways this
is perfectly illuminating because part
of the time in life it seems like
someone's doing everything right and
still they're just getting laid waste
left right and center and someone else
is doing something terribly and things
are going well for them and but then you
also see the reverse where someone who's
doing well gets rewarded and someone who
isn't doesn't so there's an ambivalence
about it now I think the story does
indicate that Cain is doing something
wrong but it it doesn't do that until
later so anyways
sorry let me just go down to the next
section here
so what it can enable sacrifice in the
biblical version cited here the nature
of Cain sacrifices left unclear except
that it is of the ground
it's vegetative and therefore bloodless
every canonical tale however carries
with it a surrounding cloud of similar
stories some derivatives some the
product of a different developmental
path and tradition some intermingled
with other stories in some variants Cain
sacrifices not only of the ground but
it's of low quality Cain is unwilling to
offer up the finest fruits of his
Labor's to God thus he does not really
sacrifice anything he wants to keep
everything good to himself so he's
selfish as well as faithless Abel by
contrast offers up the best of what he
has what does this mean
once again we already know we say to our
children do your best do not hide your
light under a bushel we do not say
conserve your best or hide your best we
mean offer the best you have do it in
good faith you will not be absolutely
assured of success but your chances will
begin to increase to the degree that
such increase is possible certainly it's
no overstatement to say that if you do
not believe this you at least wish with
all your heart that it was true this is
hope to not believe this is to risk
descent into the deepest chasms of
cynicism so what happens God accepts
Abel's sacrifice offers him respect and
renders his life acceptable despite its
terrible limitations Cain's sacrifice
however he rejects this drives Cain into
a murderous rage rage so the Lord God
had respect unto Abel and his offering
but unto Cain and his offering he did
not have respect
so the idea basically is that Abel makes
these sacrifices he's putting forth the
best that he has he's doing his best and
because of that it's actually working
everyone likes Abel you know he has he's
getting along with his wives his flocks
are increasing he's a good guy it's like
everything's going well whereas Cain
things aren't going very well at all and
no one really cares for him and besides
that he's burning with jealousy because
you know despite the fact that he's
slaving away raising all these
vegetables and trying to offer them to
God nothing is going his way
so not only are things going badly for
him but he's increasingly disaffected by
it and you know you it's not difficult
to understand that you know perfectly
well that
what happens to you if you're working
away
you think diligently and properly and
nothing is going your way and some other
son of a is just flourishing like
mad beside you that that's going to make
you vengeful and and irritated and
anxious and angry and and homicidal for
that matter and it doesn't take very
long before people reach that stage at
least not in their fantasies now the
story says and Cain was very wroth and
his countenance fell and what that meant
is he's angry and his face changes to
indicate that so he's got this continual
look of perpetual dis effect Asian and
anger on his face because things aren't
going well for him so that's fine so
then he goes and has a chat with God
because he's not very happy about the
whole situation and I think people do
that all the time too even if they don't
necessarily formulate it in those terms
it's like they're thinking well what's
the nature of reality I'm busting myself
in half here trying to make things work
properly and nothing's going well it's
like what kind of stupid universe is
that and for all intents and purposes
that's a cola coy with God because you
don't start thinking about the ultimate
fabric of reality without bringing
religious intuitions into it you can't
even ask such a question without acting
in a quasi religious manner so this is
what happens it took me a long time to
unpack this so he goes and has the chat
chat with yahwah with God and the Lord
said to Cain why are you angry and
downcast surely if you do right
you ought to hold your head high sin
crouches out your door lusting for you
yet you can master it now that's very
very interesting so I translated those I
got a translation to those lines from a
guy named Miles from 1995 now it's so
what happens is that Cain goes and has a
chat with God about how things aren't
going very well and basically what he's
trying to do is hold God to account for
why he made such a stupid universe where
everything keeps going wrong and what
God says to him is why are you angry and
downcast if you do right you ought to be
able to hold your head high so there's
an intimation there that the reason the
Cain is warned around like this is
because there's actually something he's
doing that's not correct it's not that
the structure of reality's got a problem
it's that Cain has a problem and God
says well if you just do things proper
then you could stand up you wouldn't
have to be a defeated lobster all
hunched over and aggravated you could
stand up and you know hold yourself
properly and be be thoroughly integrated
in a proper manner with the way being is
unfolding and then he says sin crutches
at your door lusting for you yet you can
master it now that's a very interesting
line so I found out that there's a
there's an under there's a metaphorical
context within which those lines are
uttered and here's the context so God
basically tells Cain that sin which is
misbehavior is a kind of personality and
the personality that he associates it
with is something like a sexually
aroused predatory cat and he tells Cain
that he's no Cain's in a house and that
thing is crouching at the door and it's
waiting to jump on it and then he tells
Cain that that's a real threat and it's
right there but he could he could not
have that happen if he wanted and
there's a there's a whole set of
inferences in there one inference is
Cain invites it in now you remember you
may not remember you have to invite a
vampire into your house it can't just
come in of its own accord you have to
open the door and so that's the first
thing God tells Cain it's like yeah yeah
sure things aren't going very well but
like that things at your door you
invited it in and you could master it if
you want but you chose not to and then
the next thing that that the the
conceptualization of the sin as this
sort of angry and lustful calf there's a
sexual connotation to it and so the
thing pounces on Cain and has its way
with him so there's an idea that there's
a like a quasi sexual interaction
between Cain and this force so that it's
a creative interplay it's not only that
he's dominated by the sin it's that he
brings it in and enters into a creative
union with it and produces something out
of the out of the mixture and so for
example when I was reading the Columbine
kid's writings it's like you can see
exactly that in their behavior it's like
he knew perfectly well what he was up to
he knew perfectly well what he was
inviting in and he put his own
extraordinarily creative twist on it it
wasn't just that he was possessed by an
idea
he spent months planning with his
horrible little compatriot about exactly
how they were going to blow up the
school and the town and they would have
liked to have blown up the whole damn
city that was part of their plan and
exactly how are they were going to turn
that into a creative spectacle that
would be covered by networks all over
the laughs perfectly consciously every
single bit of this so they put their own
twist on it as a consequence of being
angry and resentful and unhappy you know
so anyways so God tells Kane you know
why are you coming to complain to me
there's nothing wrong with reality it's
you like you get your act together and
behave properly you can stand up huh
hold your head up high and you don't
have to let this thing that's tempting
you have its way with you and enter into
a creative union with it you could just
behave properly and so Kane leaves and
then he's really annoyed and the reason
he's annoyed is because he's going in
their hope and they deal straight and
gone out with a little chat and sent
reality straight and basically what he
finds out is that as far as God is
concerned the reason that all these
terrible things are happening to him is
because he's not anywhere near what he
could be and he's setting himself up for
continual failure and so that really
annoys him so no not only is he mad
about the fact that he's failing but
he's even more mad because when he
thought it through he realized that it
was actually his fault and that the
reason these things are happening to him
is because he's not what he could be so
then you might think well what does he
do as a consequence you know you could
think well he could say well a little
apology to God and try to get himself on
the right track and that isn't what
happens at all he goes and kills Abel
with a rock now you think well why does
he do that well that's very complicated
it's partly well Abel is obviously God's
favorite so he's doing everything he can
to pull him down and you think people do
that all the time
like if you're jealous of someone else's
accomplishments these things really play
themselves out in junior high in high
school but they also play out in in
adult life you'll do everything you can
to pull down the thing that's you know
hovering above you and making you look
bad from as a consequence of the
reflection it's easier to destroy the
ideal than it is to try to live up to it
and people do that all the time and then
they're punishing each other for their
virtues and they do that because well
first of all because they can pull down
the ideal and then they don't have
the mirror that makes themselves
uncomfortable but they can also do that
as a revenge against God it's like well
if that's what you favor and you're
gonna torture me to death then I'll just
destroy what you've brought up to be the
best manifestation of what is at this
point and then we'll just see who's
who's winning this war who's winning the
war of being and so that's what happens
he goes out and kills Abel and so God
comes along it's a terrible thing
because it means he destroys his own
ideal but he's perfectly willing to pay
that price as long as he can get revenge
for his misery and his revenge on God
and it's interesting too because if you
look at the writings of people who
commit real atrocities you can see that
they've gone far beyond any desire for
individual revenge like the kids that
people that the Columbine kids shot up
in in the high school they didn't even
necessarily have any grudge against
those particular kids it was like mayhem
for mayhem sake and it was actually
better if they shot someone that was
innocent because that was a lot more of
a protest than shooting someone who was
guilty you know if you're shooting
someone who's bullied you it's like
that's just Joe that's just justice I
mean it's a warped and bent form of
justice but if you go into the high
school and shoot someone who's been good
to you well then you're really making a
statement about just what you think
about the world and if you're willing to
blow your own head off afterwards well
it's just that much more indication that
you could say to hell with everything
and that nothing is worth having and
that's like that's a that's a that's a
demonstration of that mode of thinking
right down to the bottom so anyways he
goes out there and he kills Abel I'll
read you this paragraph Cain is faced
with a very stark choice his pride his
belief in his own missions compels him
to repeat actions that do not presume
produce their desired outcome despite
their self to find failure this breeds a
deep resentment once his pride and
resentment grow past a certain threshold
he starts to fantasize about revenge and
then about murder the gap between
fantasy and action grows even smaller as
resentment builds and one day the
opportunity manifests itself Abel says
something optimistic deserving and
promising and that straw breaks the
camel's back perhaps it is at four
it is just resentment of the successful
deep resentment but it does not have to
end there there's no real end with
enough resentment you can kill once if
you can kill once why not ten if ten why
not a hundred if a hundred why not
10,000 why not a million stellen was
just getting warmed up when he killed
six million Ukrainians in the 1930s
there's evidence from the KGB archives
that Stalin was preparing for the third
world war when he was killed by his own
people in the 1950s and who's to say
that Hitler really lost the war depends
entirely on what he was aiming for
maybe he got just what he aimed for when
he blew his brains out all over his
bunker deep underneath Berlin while
Europe burned to ashes around him why do
we cyst upon believing that every tyrant
fights a war to win
Kane believed that the world was a
terrible and unreasonable place bent on
his suction suffering and destruction he
thought that hard work and sacrifice was
for babies and fools this is from
Richard the third
why should wrath be mute and fury dumb I
am no baby I that with based prayers I
should repent the evils that I have done
ten thousand worse than ever yet I did
would I perform if I might have my will
if one good deed in all my life I did I
do repent it from my very soul Eric
Harris this is from Columbine the most
literate of the two killers said I hate
the world kill mankind no one
should survive most investigators of the
Columbine killings claim they cannot
understand the boys motivations and they
could understand them they just don't
want to Harris said I would sooner die
than betray my own thoughts but before I
leave this worthless place I will kill
whoever I deem unfit Harris transformed
himself into an archetypal embodiment of
Cain whose ultimate prototype is
motivated according to Goethe by the
following principle so this is
mephistopheles the spirit I that
endlessly denies and rightly too for all
that comes to birth is fit for overthrow
as nothing worth wherefore the world
were better sterilized thus all that's
here is evil recognized as gain to me
and down full downfall rooms sin
the very element I prosper in Harris the
day before his mass murder about 26.5
hours from now the judgment will begun
begin difficult but not impossible
necessary nerve-racking and fun what fun
is life without a little death it's
interesting when I'm in my human form
knowing I'm going to die
everything has a touch of triviality to
it leader yeah so what happens then is
god finds cain and has a little chat
with him he says when you tell the
ground it will not henceforth yield unto
unto the her strength
he'll be a fugitive and a vagabond and
cain said unto the Lord my punishment is
greater than I can bear
behold thou has driven me out of this
day from the face of the earth and from
thy face shall I be hidden and I shall
be a fugitive and a vagabond on the
earth and that it shall come to pass
that everyone who finds me will slay me
and the Lord said therefore whoever
slayeth Cain vengeance shall be taken
upon him Sevenfold and the Lord said a
mark on Cain lest any finding him should
kill him now what happens in the in the
aftermath of that story seems to be
something like that
so there's Cain and then Adam and Eve
have another son whose name is Seth and
Seth produces descendants and one and
one of them down the chain is Noah and
he saves the world from the flood but
Cain produces descendants two and each
of the descendant generations seem to
get more and more aggressive and the
generation that produces a man named
tubal Cain seems to be the same
generation as Noah on the other branch
and tubal Cain is by tradition the first
person who produces our artifacts tools
of warfare and so there's an idea in the
Old Testament in this story that it's
the individual murderous resentment of
the individual who won't make the proper
sacrifices that distributes itself into
the community and culminates in
increasing brutality atrocity and
finally into war
tubal-cain tu BL dash CAI n yeah and so
Lamech is one of the one of the cain
Cain's descendants and this Islamic
Lamech kills two men when he has wounded
and hurt and Lamech says unto his wives
Adah and Zillah hear my voices he wives
of Lamech hearken unto my speech for I
have slain a man to my wounding and a
young man to my hurt if Cain shall be
Avenged Sevenfold truly Lamech seventy
and Sevenfold so there's this the idea
of the exponential distribution of
brutality into the community as a
consequence of this initial adoption of
a particular form of being okay so
here's the situation that that's laid
out in Genesis as far as I can tell is
that people emerge itself conscious and
that produces a terrible burden on
people and then the burden is even
either handled in the appropriate manner
with the proper sacrifices or it's not
if it's not the consequences are that
everything degenerates into brutality
and atrocity and that seems to me to be
approximately correct and so you can
understand both Cain enables motivations
you know Cain gets brutal and resentment
'fl because things don't go well for him
and because he's suffering and it might
be arbitrary you know and sometimes your
suffering does seem to be entirely
arbitrary but part of the moral of the
story is that if you allow that to make
you resentful and vengeful that you'll
participate in processes that make
things absolutely unbearable and make
the entire situation much worse and all
the existential commentary I've read on
the things that happened in the Second
World War and in estelle in this Soviet
Union and in China for that matter
seemed to lay out exactly the same story
which is once individuals get corrupted
because they're unhappy with the
structure of their being they can
corrupt the entire social landscape and
the entire world and things go from bad
to worse until they're as bad as they
can possibly be so that's how things go
badly you might think well how do things
go well and you know unfortunately we
missed one lecture but there's some
things that I can tell you that I that I
think I know
what what are you laughing about no no
no no well there's there's other things
that I wanted to tell you about but I
can tell you about this anyways I just
can't do it in quite as much depth as I
would have liked to so it doesn't seem
to me that it's reasonable to try to
impose an ideological solution on the
world and the reason that that's not
reasonable is because it leads you into
something that's akin to a sin of pride
you think you have the damn answer you
think you know everything and you can
impose that answer but the problem with
that is that it seems to that's as the
kind of sacrifice or that produces the
kind of sacrifices that God doesn't find
very acceptable and things go from bad
to worse so you might say well what's
the alternative what's the potential
alternative mode of being and so here's
something that you can think about and
and there's one thing that I want to
tell you about Christianity that's
relevant in this regard so you can
you'll see this in the last quarter of
the of maps of meaning when you read it
but there's there's images that have
popped up in the Middle Ages where the
tree of the tree in the in the Garden of
Eden is there again and on the one side
of the tree there are skulls and those
are being handed out by Eve and on the
other hand side there are these little
things that are there like fruits but
they're representatives of the hosts
that are given to people when they
undergo the mass in Christianity and so
those little hosts which are made out of
wheat which is a dying and resurrecting
God are like the body of the hero and so
the idea behind the mass is that in
order to overcome death you're supposed
to incorporate the body of the hero and
the body of the hero the hero is the
person in this mythological landscape
who is willing to voluntarily confront
death and will as a consequence be
reborn now I think that that can be read
at at a psychological level because we
already talked about the fact that one
of the things that happens that when
you're in deep error is that you can
allow the erroneous structure to
dissolve into something that's chaotic
and then have it reimagining that's new
the idea that's lurking behind this idea
of transformation is that you should
identify yourself not with the initial
state of order which is like a
particular way of looking at the
old and you shouldn't identify yourself
with the state of chaos that's there
when everything collapses around you but
that you should identify yourself with
the process of transformation from order
through chaos and then into a new form
of being and so the way that you
confront the fact that reality is
continually transforming is by allowing
yourself to transform with it and that's
the volunteer that's the voluntary
that's the taking on of the voluntary
that of continual voluntary death and
rebirth in the service of higher being
and we don't know the potential limits
to that you know I mean obviously in the
current situation everyone is still
faced with the possibility of ill health
and a finite lifespan and all the things
that go along with that but we don't
know the limits of our potential dynamic
flexibility and we sure do know that if
you hold on to ways of being that are
counterproductive for any length of time
that that kills you faster and makes you
more miserable well it's happening and
the same thing happens as well when
you're you know wallowing and trapped in
a chaotic situation so so here's a
hypothesis so you know one of the things
that the New Agers will tell you is that
you should follow your bliss and I have
a big problem with that because first of
all I don't think it's true and second
because Jung pointed out that if you do
follow what you find deeply meaningful
it's likely to take you to a place that
you're most afraid of and so to me
there's a barrier to enlightenment and
the barrier is that you'll face things
that will pull you apart before you'll
face things that'll put you together and
I think that what you face that will
pull you apart is all the things that
you've done in the past that have been a
sambar suboptimal those things have to
be repaired and fixed now if you put
yourself in a situation where you're
able to rectify the errors that you've
made in the past so that you straighten
out the manner in which you're organized
then I think that it might be possible
to live so that your forthrightly
confronting things as they move towards
you and if you're oriented towards
making them better like assume that
that's your highest
value say well what's the purpose of
life and the purpose of life is to make
things as good as you can possibly make
them and that might be for you and it
might be for those around you and you
might not even know exactly what that
means so sometimes you're gonna have to
let go of what you think good is as you
progress towards it well it seems to me
that if you orient yourself towards that
and you allow yourself to stop living in
in in theories that you know to be false
and carrying falsehoods that you're
acting out and and believing in that you
know to be not true that you can start
to live in a different way so here's the
different way in some sense so the first
thing you have to figure out is that you
don't know what the hell you're doing
the second you have to think to figure
out and that's humility I think the
second thing you have to figure out is
what you want and you either want things
to be better or you want them to be
worse and there's reasons for wanting
them to be worse and the reasons are
deep and they're justifiable but they're
not helpful so then let's assume that
you've noticed the part of you that's
devoted like came to the destruction of
things and you understand what that is
and you're willing to take it onto
yourself to repair then it isn't other
people's evil that you have to worry
about it's your own then you might say
well what should you do next and one of
the one of the pieces of literature from
which I've learned from that seems to
address that is the Sermon on the Mount
in the New Testament one thing that
happens in the Sermon on the Mount is
this so Christ says to his followers
that they should there there isn't
something specifically that they should
be pursuing what they should be doing
instead of orienting themselves in a
particular direction and the direction
would be towards what's best and what's
true so that's the first step as you
figure out do you want things to be
better
you want them to be worse that's the
fundamental question so are you working
for the betterment of being or for its
transformation into help and then you
think well I want things to be better
then the next thing you think is well
you don't exactly know how to go about
that okay so then what do you do well it
seems to me that that's the point at
time when you try to eradicate from your
field of apprehension everything that
you know to be false and unworthy you
get rid of it as much as you can as fast
as you can and part of the way you can
do that is by listening to what you say
and watching what you do and you can
listen to what you say and you can find
out if you're actually saying what you
believe to be true now here's a
hypothesis and I think this is the
hypothesis that's laid out in the
transformation from the Old Testament to
the New Testament in Christianity but I
also think it's the same idea that the
Daoists were pursuing and the Buddhists
were pursuing so the idea is this and
it's based on the idea of logos what
would happen if instead of pursuing what
you think you should be pursuing you did
something else which is you set yourself
in a position where you're trying to
make things better and the next
consequence of that is to try to say as
clearly as what you posit as you
possibly can
what it is that you believe to be true
in every situation and then to see what
happens it's a different way of playing
the same game now in the Sermon on the
Mount what Christ tells his followers is
to orient themselves towards paradise
and truth fundamentally and then to
concentrate on doing everything they
possibly can moment to moment as
carefully and correctly as possible and
then to see what happens so there's this
ancient idea that's at the root of
Western culture that being is spoken
into existence and that's that's this
that's the speech of the logos and and
the idea there is also partly that that
in hairs inside people if they if
they're willing to utilize it and that
they know how they can utilize it and
the way to utilize that is to straighten
out your speech in action
and to act as well as you can moment to
moment and to let go other than that and
see what happens because and I think
that that's the movement of faith that
the existentialist Christians
continually talk about you can't because
the thing is if you're aiming at
something specific that constitutes the
good then basically what you've done is
made yourself a kind of Idol you said
well this is paradise and God but the
thing is you don't know that because
you're not sufficiently informed to
understand the ultimate nature of the
good but I think you're sufficiently
informed to figure out when you're not
using your language properly and I think
one of the things that you can notice is
that if you're not using it properly it
makes you ashamed and weak and
embarrassed and I think you can feel
that you can feel it fully embodied and
I think that's what Cain does and that's
what God tells them to stop doing he
says if you're doing things right you
can stand up with your head held high
and if you're not you can't your
downcast and angry and resentful and
murderous and I think that that's the
case so and I do believe that it's a
different way of being because it's not
aimed at something it's not aimed at
something that's predefined you have to
under you have to allow what constitutes
the good and your understanding of the
good to continually be updated as you
pursue it and I think all you have to do
to do that is to speak words well
Northrop Frye would say is that you have
to speak words with power and I think
you can learn to do that but you have to
let go and I think that that's the
that's the cure for ad ology you know
because what's the alternative you can
lay out a belief system and try to
impose it or you can play along and see
if you can figure out what's going on
and if you have a productive
conversation with someone that's what
you're doing you know you say well let's
see if we can figure out how to get
along maybe this is within the confines
of an intimate relationship it's like
okay what do you want what do I want how
is that going to fit together can we
communicate honestly about exactly what
that is and how we might get it and it's
it's a process of CO discovery it's not
like you know the answer to begin with
and you're not going to find it unless
you tell each other the truth and you're
not going to be able to pursue it unless
you act out the truth that you
articulate and I don't think you're
going to be able to articulate the truth
properly unless what you want is the
good and that's a very difficult thing
to figure out but I think one of the
things we do know after the 20th century
that the continual attempt to make the
world as atrocious a place as possible
seems to be searching in the wrong
direction
no you know I've tried this sort of
thing for a very long period of time
because I think that what I try to do or
why what I try to do is to say what I
believe to be the case in every
situation that I'm in and to see what
happens and my experiences being that
really works like it really works you
can learn to get along with the people
in your family and help them straighten
out and you can start to have a
relatively beneficial effect on
processes that are outside of your you
know of what's right in front of you and
within your grasp so you can practice
trying to figure out how to set things
straight and I have no idea what the
ultimate limits of that might be but I
can tell you one thing it certainly
makes your life and ridiculously
interesting and you know that in itself
is one of the things that takes away the
sting of mortality because if what
you're doing is so damn interesting you
can hardly stand it the fact that you
have to pay a price as you move along
starts to become acceptable you know
because you'll pay a price if it's worth
it it's Nietzsche said if you have a Y
you can bear anyhow and I think there's
some truth in that and you know you
might say well what's what's a good
that's sufficiently good to justify
voluntarily participating in being
that's bent on your misery and
destruction that's the fundamental
question of life well I would say you
need a pretty elevated vision in order
to counteract that and I think that's
what a vision of paradise is and I think
that paradise is something that people
have to build I think if we build it
properly it would justify everything
that happened on the way to building it
or at least that might be the case and I
think you can do it locally first
so and I can't see and I've watched
people I've watched how people have
lived live now for decades and I have
two clients in my practice right now who
one of them was pretty damn straight to
begin with but he's set up his his
business it happens to be a firm and
he's tried to make absolutely straight
decisions that were really informed and
proper the entire way along and the
bloody thing is running like a like it's
running it's equilibrate it it's
extremely effective it's not wasteful
everybody who's inside the organization
is developing properly
no one's getting screwed over like it's
it's an honest and straightforward
enterprise and everybody seems to be
benefitting from it and I have another
client who was pretty damn confused and
arrogant and resentful when he first
started changing his life and he put
together a relatively small business and
I would say it's a low status business
but he's done it as honestly as he
possibly could and he tried to keep
himself on the straight and narrow while
he's doing it and he's trying to give
his customers outstanding service and to
be clear and straight with them at every
single choice moment and that's lifted
his cynicism and it's made his business
very very productive and and positive
and so I can't see first of all there
has to be some antidote ideology because
it's corrosive and and destructive and I
can't see that there's any any end that
you can attain at any means that you can
implement that's more meaningful and
rich and deep than that and I do think
it's sufficient to start you from being
corrupted and Jenna Seidel and that's a
good thing because you can get corrupted
in genocide 'el and if there's enough of
us who are corrupt and genocidal then
things are gonna get very bad instead of
very good so well so then you can think
about that and I think it's an easy
thing to start to try the first thing
you have to do is decide if you want
things to be better or worse and that's
not a simple question because there'll
be a lot of you that's bitter and
resentful and vengeful and angry
for all of your inadequacies and the way
the world's treated you and so and the
second thing is pay attention to what
you say and see if you believe it and if
you don't quit saying it see what
happens like you can tell if what you
say makes you strong or if it makes you
weak all you have to do is feel it and
you can stop saying things that make you
weak but it'll change you completely so
you'll find that you won't be able to
associate with people who only allow you
to say things that make you weak for
example because lots of people would be
upset if you say things that make you
strong around them because they don't
want you to flourish and grow partly
because it sheds a bad light on them
anyways this is more of elaborated in
the last quarter of the book or there
abouts and so you'll get a chance to
read that if you want to do it and I
guess I'll see you guys when you when
you have the final but in the meantime
well think about it you know I think we
have more opportunity now at this point
in history to make things good than we
could have possibly imagined 50 years
ago and it's necessary you know there's
lots of things that are falling apart
and people get cynical about that and
that's the wrong attitude it's like you
have no idea how much power you might
have at your disposal if you used it
properly and I think we could set things
right if we decided that it was worth
doing and so it certainly seems to me to
beat the alternative because in the 20th
century we bloody well learned what the
alternative was and it is as horrible as
anything you could possibly imagine so
it seems to me that it's very much worth
a while avoiding that even if we can't
make things perfect so see you all